Joseph McGirr, PhD

Evolutionary Biologist Postdoctoral Researcher

email: josephmcgirr@gmail.com

twitter: @mcgirr_joewebsite: joemcgirr.github.io

github: joemcgirr

Summary

I'm a bioinformatics scientist specializing in evolutionary genetics and population biology. I have a Ph.D. in biology from the University of North Carolina and have published research in genomics and transcriptomics in prominent journals including *Molecular Biology and Evolution, Evolution Letters*, and *Molecular Ecology*. My projects combine evolutionary theory with next generation sequencing data to answer questions at the intersection of basic and applied research.

Education

University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill 2015-2020 Ph.D. Biology
University of Colorado, Colorado Springs 2010-2014 B.S. Biology magna cum laude

Experience

2020 - Postdoctoral Researcher, Whitehead Lab, Dept. of Environmental Toxicology, University of California, Davis, CA

- Conducted temporal and spatial genomic contrasts to understand population collapse and recovery.
- Identified cross-species differential gene expression in response to osmotic stress.

2015-2020 PhD Student, Martin Lab, Dept. of Biology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC

- Research on the genetic basis of adaptive traits and reproductive isolation in young species.
- Identification of novel candidate genes influencing craniofacial development.
- Discovered alleles under divergent selection contributing to gene misregulation in hybrids.
- Taught labs in evolution, animal behavior, anatomy, and course-based undergraduate research (CURE).

2011-2014 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Bono Lab, Dept. of Biology, University of Colorado, Colorado Springs, CO

- Research on early stages of speciation in Drosophila.

Selected Publications

full list at: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=BaXHXekAAAAJ&hl=en

Few fixed variants between trophic specialist pupfish species reveal candidate *cis*-regulatory alleles underlying rapid craniofacial divergence. McGirr JA and Martin CH. 2020. *Molecular Biology and Evolution*. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaa218

Ecological divergence in sympatry causes gene misregulation in hybrids. McGirr JA and Martin CH. 2020. Molecular Ecology. https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15512

Parallel evolution of gene expression between trophic specialists despite divergent genotypes and morphologies. McGirr JA and Martin CH. *Evolution Letters*. https://doi.org/10.1002/evl3.41

Funding and Awards

Triangle Center for Evolutionary Medicine Graduate Fellowship. 2018-2019

Rosemary Grant Travel Award, Society for the Study of Evolution. 2017

L.I. Gilbert Travel Award, University of North Carolina Chapel Hill. 2017.

Best Graduate Student Presentation, Southeastern Population Ecology and Evolutionary Genetics Conference. 2018.

Skills

Code: R, python, bash.

Bioinformatics: Illumina whole genome and transcriptome alignment, annotation, and SNP calling with BWA, STAR, Trinity, GATK, samtools, ANGSD and R-Bioconductor packages.

Computing: SLURM, Amazon EC2, LSF, git. **Statistics:** Linear models, mixed models, classical stats, GWAS, genetic demographic modeling.

Bench: Designed and performed CRISPR/Cas9

gene editing experiments.